A Finding Aid to the Jerry Dreva Papers, 1964-1984, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jerry Dreva papers
1964-1984
Archives of American Art
Dreva, Jerry, 1945-1997
AAA.drevjerr
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The Jerry Dreva papers measures 1.0 linear foot and dates from circa 1963-1982. The papers include biographical information; rare printed material; scrapbooks; correspondence consisting of letters of support for the exhibition DREVA/GRONK 1968-78: Ten Years of Art/Life (Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions, 1978) and mail art; zines and small artist books exchanged with collaborators and friends; material documenting Dreva's relationship with performance artist, Gronk, including staged photographs, candid snapshots, correspondence, and ephemera, chronicling their shared practice, and the glam Hollywood, activist Chicana/o, and queer scenes in 1970s and 80s Los Angeles. Also included are two small labeled vinyl albums, one of which appears to have been used in a piece of artwork.
Biographical / Historical
Jerry Dreva (1945-1997) was a performance artist, writer, activist, and teacher based in Milwaukee, Wisconsin and Los Angeles, California. Dreva was a leader in the mail art movement during the 1970s and 1980s. He was a founding member (together with Robert J. Lambert) of Les Petites Bon-Bons, a flamboyantly attired musical group that never played a single concert. In fact, they never so much as picked up an instrument. Instead they dressed as glitter rock musicians of the era (1970's) and were frequently featured in newspapers and magazines.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2020 by Patrick Veda, a family attorney and the executor of Dreva's mother's estate.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The Jerry Dreva papers measures 1.0 linear foot and dates from circa 1963-1982. The papers include biographical information; rare printed material; scrapbooks; correspondence consisting of letters of support for the exhibition DREVA/GRONK 1968-78: Ten Years of Art/Life (Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions, 1978) and mail art; zines and small artist books exchanged with collaborators and friends; material documenting Dreva's relationship with performance artist, Gronk, including staged photographs, candid snapshots, correspondence, and ephemera, chronicling their shared practice, and the glam Hollywood, activist Chicana/o, and queer scenes in 1970s and 80s Los Angeles. Also included are two small labeled vinyl albums.
Correspondence consists of letters to friends and institutions for which Dreva created mail and graphic art for. Some of the indiduals include: Vittore Baroni, John Jack, The Gay Activists Alliance, Michael Scott, and Sandy Robertson. Also included are files of mail art created by Dreva or sent to him by friends and other artists.
Professional files consist of some invoices and receipts, material related to the "Dreva/Gronk 1968-1978 Ten Years of Art/Life" exhibition, work for Mohammed publication company in Italy, certificates, a vinyl record produced by Le Petite Bon-Bons, and a scrapbook.
Printed material consists of clippings, announcements and posters, editions of Mainman Newsletter, "Despair" comic book, "How I Became Rich and Famous" by Captain Zerox, and "Mail Art Show" exhibition catalog.
Photographic material consists of photographs of Dreva, photographs of Dreva and Gronk, photographs of Le Petite Bon-Bons band members and various famous rock stars, and candid shots.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series
Series 1: Correspondence, 1972-1983 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Professional Activity Files, 1975-1984 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1964-1979 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Photographic Material, circa 1975-1979 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Performance artists -- California -- Los Angeles; Authors -- California -- Los Angeles; Educators -- California -- Los Angeles; Gay artists; Performance artists -- Wisconsin -- Milwaukee; Mail art; Activists (LGBTQ); Artists (LGBTQ); Latino and Latin American artists; Sound recordings; Gronk, 1954-
- Correspondence, 1972-1983; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in alphabetical order. Folders of mail art are at the end of the series arranged in chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists of letters to friends and institutions for which Dreva created mail and graphic art for. Some of the indiduals include: Vittore Baroni, John Jack, The Gay Activists Alliance, Michael Scott, and Sandy Robertson. Also included are files of mail art created by Dreva or sent to him by friends and other artists.
  - Remora Coast, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A-C, 1972-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Count Fanzini, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - D-H, 1972-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John Jack, 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - I-N, 1973-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sandy Robertson, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - O-R, 1973-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Michael Scott, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - S-Z, 1974-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mail Art, 1974-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Professional Activity Files, 1973-1984; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Professional files consists of some invoices and receipts, material related to the "Dreva/Gronk 1968-1978 Ten Years of Art/Life" exhibition, work for Mohammed publication company in Italy, certificates, a vinyl record produced by Le Petite Bon-Bons, and a scrapbook.
  Series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Invoices and Receipts, 1973-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Dreva/Gronk 1968-78 Ten Years of Art/Life" Exhibition, 1974, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notes Towards an Interview and Beyond, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mohammed, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Certificates, circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Revolutionary Peoples Constitutional Convention, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bon Bon Record, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound discs (vinyl) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mail Art Scrapbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1975-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Printed Material, 1964-1979; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Printed material consists of clippings, announcements and posters, editions of Mainman Newsletter, "Despair" comic book, "How I Became Rich and Famous" by Captain Zerox, and "Mail Art Show" exhibition catalog.
  - Clippings, 1964-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Announcements and Posters, 1967-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "20th Century Fun, A Selection of Songs by Ian Whitcomb", 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mainman Newsletters, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "How I Became Rich and Famous" by Captain Zerox, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Dead Fingers Talk...", 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Patti, de lame pour lame", 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Patti Smith Rockin' Demonia, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Despair" Comic Book, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Phallus: A Book of Dreams" by John Duncan, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Mail Art Show" Exhibition Catalog, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Gary Gilmore's Eyes", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Photographic Material, circa 1975-1979; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Photographic material consists of photographs of Dreva, photographs of Dreva and Gronk, photographs of Le Petite Bon-Bons band members and various famous rock stars, and candid shots.
  - Jerry Dreva, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Dreva and Gronk, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Les Petite Bon-Bons and Various Rock Groups and Artists, circa 1976-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Exhibitions and Performances, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)